Chapter 11. Night gown.
We had lain thus in bed, chatting and napping at short intervals, and Quiquake
now and then affectionately throwing his brown tattooed legs over mine, and then
drawing them back, so entirely sociable and free and easy were we, when, at
last, by reason of our confabulations, what little nappishness remained in us
altogether departed, and we felt like getting up again, though daybreak was
yet some way down the future. Yes, we became very wakeful, so much so that our
recumbent position began to grow weariesome, and by little and little we
found ourselves sitting up, the clothes well tucked around us, leaning against
the headboard with our fore knees drawn up close together and our two noses
bending over them, as if our knee pans were warming pants. We felt very nice
and snug, the more so since it was so chilly out of doors. Indeed, out of bed
clothes, too, seeing that there was no fire in the room. The more so, I say,
because truly to enjoy bodily warmth, some small part of you must be cold. For
there is no quality in this world that is not what it is merely by contrast.
Nothing exists in itself. If you flatter yourself that you are all over
comfortable and have been so for a long time, then you cannot be said to be
comfortable anymore. But if like Quiquake and me in the bed, the tip of
your nose or the crown of your head be slightly chilled, why then indeed in the
general consciousness you feel most delightfully and unmistakably warm. For
this reason, a sleeping apartment should never be furnished with a fire, which is
one of the luxurious discomforts of the rich. For the height of this sort of
deliciousness is to have nothing but the blanket between you and your snugness
and the cold of the outer air. Then there you lie like the one warm spark in
the heart of an arctic crystal.
We had been sitting in this crouching manner for some time when all at once I
thought I would open my eyes. For when between sheets, whether by day or by
night, and whether asleep or awake, I have a way of always keeping my eyes
shut, in order, the more to concentrate on these snugness of being in bed,
because no man can ever feel his own identity or right, except his eyes be
closed, as if darkness were indeed the proper element of our essences, though
light be more congenial to our clay part. Upon opening my eyes then, and
coming out of my own pleasant and self-created darkness into the imposed
and coarse outer gloom of the unilluminated 12:00 at night, I
experienced a disagreeable revulsion.
Nor did I at all object to the hint from Quiqu that perhaps it were best to
strike a light, seeing that we were so wide awake, and besides, he felt a
strong desire to have a few quiet puffs from his tomahawk. Be it said that
though I had felt such a strong repugnance to his smoking in the bed the
night before, yet see how elastic our stiff prejudices grow when love comes
once to bend them. For now I like nothing better than to have Quiquake
smoking by me, even in bed, because he seemed to be full of such serene
household joy then. I no more felt unduly concerned for the landlord's
policy of insurance. I was only alive to the condensed confidential
comfortableness of sharing a pipe and a blanket with a real friend. With our
shaggy jackets drawn about our shoulders, we now passed the tomahawk
from one to the other, till slowly there grew over us a blue hanging tester of
smoke, illuminated by the flame of the new lit lamp. Whether it was that this
undulating tester rolled the savage away to far distant scenes, I know not. But
he now spoke of his native island, and eager to hear his history, I begged him
to go on and tell it. He gladly complied, though at the time I but ill
comprehended not a few of his words, yet subsequent disclosures, when I had
become more familiar with his broken phrasiology, now enable me to present
the whole story, such as it may prove in the mere skeleton I give.